Geer (Andrew) papers M2257
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Andrew C. Geer papers
c. 1913-1969
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Geer, Andrew Clare
M2257
10.6 Linear Feet 12 MB, 2 half boxes, 4 flat boxes
Biographical / Historical
Andrew C. Geer first served in North Africa with the American Field Service, and then in the United States Marine Corps in both WWII and Korea, eventually being promoted to Captain. He wrote books and published stories in various magazines. His most acclaimed published books were The New Breed: the story of the U. S. Marines in Korea; The Sea Chase, a drama set in WWII which was made into a movie starring John Wayne and Lana Turner; and Reckless: Pride of the Marines, about a decorated war horse who won two purple hearts.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains 10 typed manuscripts of Andrew Geer's books, issues of magazines where his stories were published, and many newspaper clippings about his work. The photographs show him in the military, as a civilian, as an author, and in private life. The large quantity of personal letters includes those to his wife both prior to and after their marriage. The collection includes photographs and a scrapbook about Sergeant Reckless, the beloved decorated war horse of the USMC, as well as Geer's manuscript of his published book called Reckless. The collection includes the manuscript and storyboard of Geer's book turned movie, The Seachase, starring a stellar cast including Johm Wayne and Lana Turner.
Materials in the collection consist of correspondence, manuscripts, printed material, scrapbooks, photographs and physical artifacts such as serving medals composed by and belonging to Andrew C. Geer.
General
Andrew C. Geer (1905-1957) was a Marine Corps officer and author.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robert W. Taggart; 2017. Accession MSS 2017-248.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research; material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Authors, American -- 20th century.; United States. Marine Corps. Marine Division, 1st -- History; United States. Marine Corps. Marine Regiment, 5th -- History; American Field Service -- History; Geer, Andrew Clare; Sergeant Reckless, (Horse), approximately 1948-1968
- Series 1. Personal Information and Documents
  - Biographical information, including letter to Jane which includes memories from childhood and life perspectives (Half-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Documents, including birth register, appointment to Captain, special recognition, certificates and awards including Award of Gold Star, and correspondence relating to these and to transfer - recommendation by headquarters, United States Passport, British Red Cross Certificate of Identity (Half-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Contracts, motion picture rights, and publishing rights (Half-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, published remarks and photographs relating to death (also see flat box 10, folder 3) (Half-box 1, Folder 4, Flat-box 10)
  - Documents: Resolution in Memoriam for Board of Supervisors to adjourn its meeting; Baptism certificate; appointment to Lieutenant Colonel on the United States Marine Corps Reserve (Flat-box 10, Folder 4)
  - Letter from Assistant Deputy Minister for Deputy Minister La Fleche, Department of National Defence, Ottawa, Canada, detailing activity of Canadian Mounted Rifles regiments, 1939-02 (Half-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Report of Section One, 1st CC, AFS to Colonel Ralph Richmond, Ghq, Cairo, 1942-04 (Half-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter to Major William Ingram, summarizing military experience, 1943-05 (Half-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bronze Star Medal; War Medal 1939-45; The Africa Star; The 1939-45 Star; British 8th Army badge; dog tags; desk name plate of Capt. A. Geer made from a piece of the USS Oklahoma sunk Dec 7, 1941 at Pearl Harbor; sports emblems on a chain (Box 18)
- Series 2. Manuscripts, Fiction
  - Hard is the Stone (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - The Turn of the Furrow (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - The Fight to the Sea (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - To Walk Alone (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Hard Is the Stone (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
  - Merchant Marine (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Merchant Marine with annotations (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
  - High Rolls the Tide (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - The Sea Chase (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - The Sea Chase - preliminary scene block (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The Sea Chase - storyboard (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Reckless (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Reckless - publisher's galley sheets (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
- Series 3. Published Stories
  - Fiction published in magazines: The American Magazine, Annual Scoop, Catholic Digest, The Link, Leatherneck, Redbook Magazine, The Villagers (Half-box 7)
  - Fiction published in magazines: American Weekly, Collier's, Saturday Evening Post, Town & Country (Flat-box 8)
- Series 4. Scrapbooks
  - The Story of "Sergeant Reckless" Arranged and Edited by Andrew Geer, limited edition, 1 of 6 copies (Flat-box 9)
  - The Story of "Sergeant Reckless" arranged and edited by Andrew Geer, limited edition, 1 of 6 copies (Flat-box 9)
  - Photographs and newspaper clippings of Sergeant Reckless (loose) (Flat-box 9, Folder 1)
  - The New Breed - articles and clippings from newspapers and magazines praising the book (Flat-box 9)
  - The Sea Chase - articles and clippings from newspapers and magazines praising the book, Album is fragile and many clippings have come loose. (Flat-box 10)
  - The Sea Chase - articles and clippings from newspapers and magazines praising the book, as well as promotional materials (Flat-box 10, Folder 1)
- Series 5. Photographs
  - Photograph of Andy Geer and John Wayne, The Sea Chase (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Large family photograph, mounted (Flat-box 10, Folder 4)
  - "Casualty in Korea," photograph that won $2000 frist prize in the color division of the $25,000 Photography magazine contest for 1952 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Shots from filming The Sea Chase (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Letter from cartoon creator of Snuffy Smith to Major General Wm C. Clement (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Various photos of Andy Geer as an adult (16 total) (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - 3 large photographs of Andy Geer with his wife, smaller ones with females, early family portraits, and small photographs of people some of whom are mentioned in his letters (Marmin, Myra); some photographs have notations (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Scenes in the field, military, various people and other (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Black and white photographs of a man, one of a couple (March 1935) and a group photo in the snow; various from 1943-1944; one from December 14, 1950 of Yudanm-ni; Far East from 1950-51 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Andy Geer with wife and others at a banquet table August 8, 1951; Major Andy Geer with E. W. Le Baron and others February 8, 1952; Major Andy Geer at speaker's table with Edmund Grainer, Faye Reeder, Ed Stodel and also showing General Keller Rockey and William Saal; Andy Geer at a banquet table in Hong Kong (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Andy Geer August - October 1953; in uniform with 2 men photographed by the San Francisco Examiner November 1957; various others both in uniform and not (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Photograph of Andy Geer, holding his hat, and the maroon frame it was in (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Loose photographs that were inside the album depicting travel through Tahiti, Fiji and the Tongan Islands (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Photo album depicting travel through Tahiti, Fiji, and the Tongan Islands, with some descriptions (Box 11)
- Series 6. Correspondence and Personal Letters, The letters have been foldered very roughly, both by author of the letter and the year.
  - Personal letters from Edith, 1926 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  - Letters from various people, 1926 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Personal letters from mother, 1932 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Personal letters, many from Vera, 1932-1934 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Personal letters from Fergie, 1933-1934 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Personal letters, many from Cotesty, 1933-1934 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Personal letters from Judy, 1934 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Personal letters from Julie, 1932 (Box 13, Folder 1-3)
  - Personal letters to Julie, 1932 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Personal letters from friends and family, 1933-1934 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Personal letters, many from Myra Kuehl, 1933-1935 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Letters from various people, 1932-1935 (Box 14, Folder 2-5)
  - Letters from various people, 1932-1935 (Box 15, Folder 1-4)
  - Financial correspondence: loans, life insurance (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Letters (2) to George (1945); a letter from Reese (1957); memo to Evan Thomas from Fitz with note to Andy (1948) (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Letters about The Sea Chase (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Letters about The New Breed; promotional brochure for Canton Barrier (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Letters to and from Jane Roselle, later Jane Geer, bulk 1934-1935, 1944-1945 (Box 16, Folder 1-5)
- Series 7. Jane Geer: Photographs, Letters, and Ephemera
  - Photographs from albums and from boxes (Box 17, Folder 1-3)
  - Photographs, mostly of Jane and Andy Geer (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, mostly of Andy Geer, from Jane's boxes (Box 17, Folder 5-6)
  - Personal letters (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clippings, many about Andy Geer (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Ephemera, including cards, post cards of Guatemala, 2 poems (typed), receipts, roster with names and addresses, hotel logos, negative showing a couple (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - War ration book with stamps (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Letters, cards, tickets (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - United States passport (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Wedding announcement and printing plate, congratulatory cards, newspaper clippings about announcement, 4 photos outside in the snow, can of film labeled wedding pix (Box 17, Folder 12)
- Series 8. Other
  - Jessie E. de Buda estate documents (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ephemera including hand drawn card of man with a hat with various signatures, Geo. G. Pomeroy 11/19/53 Bohemia (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ephemera including cards, YMCA card, San Francisco/Oakland decal, 2 letters to Major Geer from children, clippings mentioning Andy Geer (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The Holy Bible engraved with Andrew C. Geer, "To Andy from Marmion, January 10, 1934" (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Various newspaper articles mentioning Andrew Geer (Flat-box 10, Folder 2)